<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An apology for the sentiment of the modalists and a defence of the scriptural terms.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75506</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3556A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC N52941</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896491</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896491</idno>
            <idno type="VID">131897</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75506)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 131897)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2416:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An apology for the sentiment of the modalists and a defence of the scriptural terms.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Drop-head title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Incarnation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:131897:1"/>
            <head>An <hi>Apology</hi> for the Sentiment of the <hi>Modaliſts;</hi> and a <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Scriptural Terms.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TO defend the Doctrines of the <hi>Trinity</hi> and <hi>Incarnation</hi> requires not many Arguments, when theſe matters are rightly taken, for in order to vindicate them, they need only be repreſented and put into a true light. As for the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> it has been ſufficiently clear'd, even in the Pamphlet intitled, <hi>The Conſequences of the Modaliſts Syſtem,</hi> p. 8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For there theſe Remarks are made concerning it The Divine <hi>Intellect,</hi> or Mind and Underſtanding, is the <hi>Cauſe</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Divine <hi>Wiſdom;</hi> and from both the Divine <hi>Intellect</hi> and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> doth <hi>proceed</hi> the Divine <hi>Will</hi> or <hi>Power,</hi> which is the ſame thing in a perfect Being, for God <hi>doth</hi> whatſoever he <hi>pleaſes.</hi> Theſe three <hi>Properties,</hi> Intellect, Wiſdom, Power, comprehend the whole Divine <hi>Eſſence</hi> God may be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly and diſtinctly conſider'd with reſpect to each of theſe <hi>three</hi> Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and thus being <hi>thrice</hi> conſider'd may be call'd <hi>three Perſons,</hi> according to the original Signification of the word <hi>Perſon,</hi> which imports <hi>a Being conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd with reſpect to a certain Capacity or Property.</hi> The firſt Property being the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of the ſecond, and the third <hi>proceeding</hi> from the two former, the firſt Perſon is therefore call'd the <hi>Father,</hi> the ſecond the <hi>Son,</hi> the third the <hi>Spirit that proceeds</hi> from the Father and Son. Thus the Orthodox Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are ſuſceptible of a good Senſe; and pertainly, meaning this Senſe by theſe Terms, it cannot be deny'd but that <hi>the Sentiment of the Modaliſts</hi> is true: It is actually true, that there is in God on infinite <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and <hi>Will,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And as for the Doctrine of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> one would think there could be no great difficulty in it, intending thereby, as the Catholic Church doth, that the Divine <hi>Wiſdom</hi> ſo <hi>dwelleth</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>always to aſſiſt, illuminate-conduct and actuate him;</hi> Chriſt thus being, <hi>God,</hi> 
               <q>in reſpect of the <hi>Indwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> Divinity, which is in an <hi>content</hi> manner <hi>manifeſted</hi> both i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and by out Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as alſo in reſpect of his <hi>repreſenting</hi> God to us, and of his <hi>acting in the ſtead of God,</hi>
               </q> at the Helm of the Univerſe</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:131897:2"/>
            <p>Yet ſome weighty Objections are here made; as <q>that this confounds Chriſt with God, and is the occaſion that the Names of Chriſt are given to God, and Chriſt is taken to be literally the moſt High God; as if from a Being's dwelling in a Temple, it follow'd that the Houſe or Temple is lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally that Being which dwelleth in it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now it is to be obſerv'd, in anſwer hereunto, that the Doctrine of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation doth not neceſſarily confound Chriſt with God; for all that can be underſtood thereby, agreeably to the Syſtem of the Modaliſts, who are generally eſteem'd to be the moſt Orthodox, is, that our Saviour is both <hi>God</hi> and <hi>the Man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> or that <hi>the Man Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and <hi>God</hi> are moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently <hi>united</hi> together in the work of <hi>Salvation,</hi> in that Chriſt is made the Head of the Church and plac'd at the Helm of the Univerſe, and God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly aſſiſts and actuates him, to enable him to ſave thoſe that come to God thro him; and thus Chriſt is evidently <hi>diſtinguiſh'd</hi> from God, by Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly being meant <hi>the Man Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed it is very improper to give to God the Names of Chriſt, as it ſeeme to be done in theſe Invocations, <hi>O Chriſt hear us, O Son of</hi> David <hi>have mercy upon us,</hi> &amp;c. But the Orthodox do readily acknowledg the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency of theſe Expreſſons; <hi>Athanaſius</hi> himſelf declares, <hi>that it is always God, and not the Creature, that is worſhip'd by the Orthodox,</hi> (<hi>3d Oration</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Arians</hi>) ſo that theſe Invocations are to be underſTood as implying this Senſe, <hi>O thou who dwelleſt in</hi> Chriſt, or <hi>in</hi> the Son of <hi>David,</hi> hear us, and hve mercy upon us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And undoubtedly it were well, if the ſaid Pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> were thus expreſs'd. Moſt properly the Goſpel-Method is to pray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ther in the Name, or thro the Mediation and Interceſſion of his Son, our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; ſo that after having ſaid in the beginning of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany, <hi>O God our Creator have mercy upon us, O God our Redeemer have mercy upon us, O God our Comfortere have mercy upon us,</hi> it would be moſt proper to addreſs the reſt of the Prayer particularly to the Father, who eminently ſuſtains the Majeſty and Character of the Deity. The ordinary Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions that follow from taking another Method, ſeem often uncouth, and much muſt tacitly be ſupply'd thereto, not to take them in a wrong Senſe, as the Vulgar are very apt to do; men of ordinary Capacities not being accuſtom'd to nice Diſtinctions, and not being able to make any deep Reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of themſelves. Beſides, it is certain that when the Father is worſhip'd, the whole Deity is worſhip'd, and our Prayers then cannot be defective or imperfect.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s being or not being <hi>the moſt High God,</hi> that is in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure a <hi>Diſpute of Words.</hi> The Deity that dwelleth in Chriſt, is certainly <hi>the moſt High God:</hi> If then by <hi>Chriſt</hi> be meant both the Man Jeſus, and the Deity that dwelleth in or that conſtantly aſſiſteth him; no dobut, in that ſenſe, Chriſt is <hi>the moſt High God.</hi> But if <hi>Chriſt</hi> be taken as an Appellation peculiar to the Man Jeſus, as it ſeems to be in Scripture; then it is <hi>moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> to ſay with the Scripture, that <hi>in Chriſt Jeſus dwelleth the Fulneſs of the Godhead:</hi> to eſteem otherwiſe, were to aſſert that an Appellation peculiar to the Manhood is peculiar to the Godhead. No body will ſay that a Man,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:131897:2"/>as a Man, is literally the moſt high God; but our Salvation being wrought both by the Man Chriſt Jeſus and God that dwelleth in him, it is certain that our Saviour is both God and Man, as ſometime ſeveral Men make one Admiral, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ideas may arbitrarily be join'd to certain Terms, and then thoſe Terms are underſtood according to thoſe Ideas. Accordingly the Church has us'd the Name <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to denote <hi>both the Man</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>and the Deity</hi> that manifeſteth it ſelf in and by him; and has us'd the Term <hi>Incarnation</hi> to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify the Union of God with Jeſus Chriſt. In that ſenſe the Church ſaith, that Chriſt is God, and that God is become Man. But ſhe means to be ſure, and ought to mean no more but what may be worded in the Expreſſions them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of the Scripture; which Expreſſions, or the like, in Articles of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, are even to be left in that general Senſe which they are ſuſceptible of, that every man may be allow'd the Judgment of diſcerning. Theſe Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations muſt be before our eyes, whenever we will give a rational account of the Orthodox Syſtem.</p>
            <p>It is objected by ſome, <q>That, meaning what has been ſaid by the Incarnation, and on that account giving to Chriſt the Honor and Name of God, the like might be done to other Creatures, which God likewiſe <hi>aſſiſts</hi> or <hi>enables</hi> to perform their ſeveral Officers, and <hi>in</hi> and <hi>by</hi> which God <hi>manifeſts</hi> his Wiſdom, his Glory and Majeſty. (Thus any one of the <hi>Prophets</hi> might have been ſaid to be God, and God incarnate, for <hi>God was with them,</hi> and inſpir'd them; the <hi>Temple of Jeruſalem</hi> might alſo, on theſe Principles, have been ſaid to be God, for God in an extraordinary manner <hi>dwelt therein;</hi> and the ſame, in fine, may be ſaid of the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon,</hi> and <hi>the whole World,</hi> for <hi>therein and thereby God manifeſts his Wiſdom and Glory</hi>) Yet it would certainly be <hi>Idolatry,</hi> on theſe or the like accounts, to call any Parts of the <hi>World,</hi> or any <hi>Prophets,</hi> or even any <hi>Angels</hi> or <hi>glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Saints,</hi> God; and undoubtedly it would be damnable Idolatry, and <hi>a Work of the Fleſh,</hi> to take them for God, and honour them as God: Why then ſhould it not alſo be reckon'd <hi>Idolatry,</hi> on this account to call Chriſt God, and to take him for the moſt High God, becauſe God dwells with him, aſſiſts him, and manifeſts his Wiſdom in him?</q>
            </p>
            <p>If this Difficulty be reſolved, that is all that the Orthodox need to do, and indeed all they can do. For to pretend a more <hi>groſs</hi> Incarnation than what has been own'd and aſſerted, would not only be contrary to the Truth, to Reaſon and Scripture, but would alſo be a <hi>Petitio Principii,</hi> ſeeing that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conteſtably it is not cler and evident, to ſay no more of it. If any man would lay it down as certainly reveal'd in Scripture, that there are three infinite and divine Spirits (which indeed would be to aſſert three Gods) and that one of theſe infinite Spirits is incarnate in a human Body <hi>after the groſſeſt manner</hi> imaginable, and would make the Belief of this an Article of Communion; he would herein do no better than <hi>beg</hi> his own Aſſertion, which is deny'd him, and ſo would ſet himſelf up for the Judg of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, and deny to other Chriſtians their Judgment of diſcerning. That cannot then and ought not to be our Refuge, in order to reſolve the foregoing Difficulty.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:131897:3"/>
            <p>And if God is but one Spirit, as the Modaliſts with good reaſon aſſert, there can be no ground left to take the <hi>Incarnation</hi> in a <hi>groſs</hi> Senſe. For it cannot be ſaid that this one Spirit is thus <hi>groſly</hi> incarnate, for then the whole Godhead were incarnate, which is contrary to the Notion of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox. The Orthodox hold that it is the Divine Wiſdom only that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate. The Incarnation therefore can reaſonably be taken but to imply was has been ſaid, namely, <q>That the Divine <hi>Wiſdom</hi> ſo <hi>dwelleth</hi> in Chriſt, as <hi>always to aſſiſt, illuminate, conduct and actuate him;</hi> and that the Divine Majeſty is <hi>manifeſted,</hi> and is in an <hi>extraordinary</hi> manner <hi>preſent</hi> in Chriſt, our Lord Jeſus Chriſt <hi>repreſenting</hi> God to us, and <hi>acting in the ſtead of God</hi> at the Helm of the Univerſe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This laſt Particular, which is the very Eſſence of what is meant by the Incarnation rationally underſtood, is not in the leaſt taken notice of in the foregoing Objection. The Objection ſuppoſes, that by the Incarnation is only meant a <hi>Manifeſtation</hi> of the Divine Wiſdom <hi>in,</hi> and a <hi>Co-operation with</hi> Chriſt, or the like. And indeed if it was ſo, the <hi>Prophets,</hi> the <hi>Temple of Jeruſalem,</hi> the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon,</hi> and all other <hi>Creatures</hi> which God co-ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates with, and in and by which he manifeſts his Wiſdom, might be call'd <hi>God,</hi> as well as Chriſt, tho not with altogether ſo great reaſon, ſeeing the Divine Co-operation and Manifeſtation is greater in Chriſt than in any other Creature, and may be ſaid in him to be extraordinary. But that which alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether diſtinguiſheth Chriſt from all other Creatures, which makes the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wiſdom and Majeſty moſt extraordinarily preſent in him, and which may authorize the giving him the Name of the moſt High God, and the honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and worſhipping the moſt High God in him, is, That this Man Chriſt Jeſus (in whom dwelleth the Divine Wiſdom, or in whom the Divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is manifeſted, and whom the Divine Wiſdom always aſſiſts, illuminates, conducts and actuates) <hi>in a moſt eminent manner repreſents God to us, being the Heir of all things, and Lord of Lords, having a Supreme Authority over all Creatures, ruling and governing all things under God, and acting in the ſtead of God at the Helm of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe, all things being ſubjected unto him by God's Decree.</hi> It is God's own Authority and Majeſty that he is inveſted with. He may therefore be ſaid to be God in that reſpect, and this Divine Majeſty and Authority may be ador'd in him.</p>
            <p>This Conſideration was altogether overlook'd in the Objection; and yet this Article (that all Power is committed to Chriſt, that he repreſents God to us, or is God's Vicegerent, and acts in the ſtead of God at the Helm of the Univerſe) is not and cannot be deny'd by any that receive the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as their Rule. Herein therefore we are not guilty of any <hi>Petitio Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipii.</hi> We mean neither more nor leſs than all thoſe muſt needs mean, and do actually mean, who own the Scripture. We do not therefore take away from any body the Judgment of diſcerning. We do not act as if we were to be, and as if we were actually magiſterial Judges of Controverſies. We inſiſt only on what is clear and undeniable.</p>
            <p>It may perhaps be ſaid, <q>That tho Chriſt be inveſted with <hi>Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> over all Creatures, yet his Authority is not <hi>abſolutely ſupreme</hi> like
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:131897:3"/>that of God, ſeeing <hi>he is himſelf ſubject</hi> to God; and it is not plain and undeniable that ever the Scripture expreſly calls Chriſt the moſt High God, or expreſly orders that Chriſt ſhould be look'd upon as the moſt High God: the Modaliſts therefore cannot enjoin that Practice, or the uſe of ſuch Expreſſions, without violating <hi>the Goſpel-Terms of Communion,</hi> or without ſetting themſelves up as magiſterial Judges of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, and without taking from others the Judgment of diſcerning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now, in anſwer to this, it cannot be deny'd but that we ſhould all keep to the Expreſſions and general Senſe of Scripture. It is <hi>the Sentiment</hi> it ſelf of the Modaliſts which I vindicate, and not any thing elſe. I have ſhewn, that the Modaliſts <hi>mean</hi> neither more nor leſs than all thoſe do, who receive the Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament. If any do ſcruple the uſe of any unſcriptural Expreſſions, God forbid that I ſhould appear as an Adverſary againſt them. But this only I ſay with <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> that we do not worſhip the Creature, but that it is God we worſhip in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thus to uſe a Compariſon, tho ſomewhat imperfect, the Queen's Majeſty is honour'd in her Viceroy in <hi>Ireland.</hi> As long as the Viceroy doth truly diſcharge his Office according to his Commiſſion, he truly bears the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of, and truly repreſents the Royal Authority. It would be impertinent to diſpute, whether then the Viceroy's Authority be truly the Supreme Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity it ſelf. Indeed the Man himſelf is ſubject to another, but ſo is not the Authority by which he acts: Certainly the Authority by which he acts is the Supreme Authority, and therefore the Supreme Authority ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected in him. Here perhaps men may differ in the manner of expreſſing themſelves; but yet all thoſe who acknowledg the Queen's Authority, and who therefore obey her Viceroy's Commands, according to her Will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd in the Commiſſion, cannot but actually agree in the thing, and mean actually the ſame thing. This Compariſon, how imperfect ſoever it be, doth in a ſufficient meaſure illuſtrate the matter before us. We may ſay, that Chriſt is the moſt High God; but by this his Supreme Godhead meaning the Divine Authority thta appears in him, we ſay no more than what others mean, when they expreſs themſelves in other Terms, namely, that in him dwells the Fulneſs of the Godhead.</p>
            <p>God will not indeed have his Glory be given to another; neither do we aſcribe Divinity but to God himſelf: For ſtill the Authority by which Chriſt acts, is God's own Authority; and we do not of our own accord, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God's warrant, aſſert it to be in Chriſt. Now when God ſays he will not give his Glory to another, the meaning viſibly is this, that he wills not that Men of themſelves, and according to their own Fancies, ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of the Honour and Glory that is due to him. As for God himſelf, he may communicate of his own without doing any wrong; and his meaning was not that he never would thus communicate himſelf, he has not ty'd his own hands; the queſtion was not what himſelf might do, but what his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were not to preſume of themſelves to do. Thus the Queen of <hi>England</hi> may ſay ſhe will not give her Glory to another, and yet ſhe may order the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:131897:4"/>ſame Honors to be paid to her Viceroy which are only due to her, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed terminate on her Majeſty wherever they are paid according to her Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but which could not lawfully be render'd to her in the Perſon of him who is her Viceroy, before her Declaration of her Will and Pleaſure in this matter and the delivering of the Viceroy's Commiſſion. Notwithſtanding this ſaying of God, that he will not give his Glory to another, the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox believe that he has given himſelf and ſo his Glory to the Man Chriſt Jeſus. Howbeit, after all it is certain God has but ſo given his Glory to Jeſus Chriſt, as that it ſtill remains his own Glory, and the ſaid Glory after all truly is aſcrib'd to and terminates on God.</p>
            <p>Tho God's Lieutenant, inaſmuch as he repreſents God to us, be term'd God, becauſe the Supreme Authority he appears inveſted with is God's own Authority; yet it cannot truly be ſaid that we make a Creature God, or hold one for God that is only a Creature: for it is God or the Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and Supreme Authority we conſider and adore in Jeſus Chriſt, for in Jeſus Chriſt dwelleth the Fulneſs of the Godhead; and when we ſay that Jeſus Chriſt is God, we mean it in reſpect of the Deity, or the Divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Majeſty and Authority that dwell in him. If any think it not ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per upon that account to call Chriſt the moſt High God, it is true it would be moſt proper to content our ſelves to ſay with the Scripture, that the Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Godhead dwelleth in the Man Chriſt Jeſus. Howbeit, the Deity that dwelleth in the Man Chriſt Jeſus, and is communicated to him as has been ſaid, is truly and properly the moſt High God, or the Majeſty, Wiſdom and Supreme Authority of the moſt High God; and that is all we mean by the Orthodox Expreſſions, but we do not intend that it is the Creature that is the moſt High God.</p>
            <p>But (to prove that it is <hi>Idolatry</hi> to call Chriſt God, and to honour him as God, upon the account that God dwelleth in him by Manifeſtation of his Wiſdom in and by him, and on the account that God conſtantly aſſiſteth him in the diſcharge of his Office of repreſenting God and acting in the ſtead of God at the Helm of the Univerſe) ſome urge, <q>That it would be <hi>trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable</hi> to give the Name of the Sovereign to the Viceroy, on any account whatſoever, whether upon the account of repreſenting, or upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of being upheld by the Sovereign, or upon the account of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign's Majeſty appearing and dwelling in him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>To this I ſhall reply thus much. In that caſe the fault would be only in the <hi>Expreſſion,</hi> but not in the <hi>Sentiment</hi> it ſelf; and ſo this would be only a <hi>Controverſy of Words.</hi> And beſides, there is this difference in the preſent Compariſon, that in an earthly Sovereign, who is a finite and imperfect Being, the Sovereign's Wiſdom, Majeſty and Authority are different from the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign's own Perſon; but it is an Axiom of Divines, <hi>That every thing in God is God,</hi> and it is upon this Axiom that it is ſaid that Chriſt is God, upon the account that the Divine Wiſdom and Majeſty in a ſupreme degree appear and dwell in him; or elſe by Chriſt we mean both the Man Jeſus Chriſt, and the Divine Wiſdom and Majeſty that dwell in him.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:131897:4"/>
            <p>Howbeit, as to the Practice of honouring Chriſt as God, that is counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanc'd by the Example of the Viceroy's being honour'd like the Sovereign. In the Perſon of the Viceroy the Sovereign is honour'd; and the Scripture likewiſe commands, that every Knee ſhould bow to Chriſt <hi>to the Glory of God.</hi> The Viceroy in publick Solemnities wherein he repreſents the Sovereign, might be ddreſs'd unto, as being the Sovereign upon the account of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign's Authority by which he acts, and which is preſent in him or dwells in him, whilſt he diſcharges his Office: If that were uſual, it would not at all ſeem ſtrange or unreaſonable.</p>
            <p>There is yet this difference in the ſaid Compariſon, that an earthly Viceroy may prove a Rebel, but this cannot be ſaid of Chriſt. We are ſure that Chriſt's Laws are God's Laws, Chriſt's Kingdom is God's Kingdom, Chriſt's Majeſty is God's Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Chriſt doth not require of us any Services that are carnal or vicious, and that may be term'd <hi>Works of the Fleſh,</hi> as did the Pagan Gods. The Gods of the Heathens were worſhip'd by the Slaughter of human Sacrifices, by Proſtitutions, and by other corrupt and immoral Practices. Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us to worſhip the Father in Spirit and in Truth, and directs us to ask all things of God in his name, or as his Diſciples, and for his ſake. And the Orthodox declare, that this is all they intend to do, howſoever they expreſs themſelves. What <hi>Idolatry</hi> then, or what <hi>Work of the Fleſh</hi> is here?</p>
            <p>There can be ſuppos'd, one would think, but an Impropriety of Speech, in ſaying that the Man Jeſus Chriſt is truly and properly the moſt High God, meaning that the moſt High God, or the Divine Wiſdom, Majeſty and Supreme Authority do truly and properly appear in him. Howbeit, the <hi>Meaning</hi> and <hi>Sentiment</hi> of the Modaliſts is certainly good. And now the Reſult of all that has been ſaid, ſeems to be as followeth.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That ſome Perſons may condeſcend to the uſe of unſcriptural Terms.</item>
               <item>2. That others, who are no leſs ſincere, may ſcruple the uſe of them.</item>
               <item>3. That thoſe, on whom it is incumbent, ſhould eſtabliſh the <hi>Scriptural</hi> or <hi>Goſpel Terms of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Some Perſons may condeſcend to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of unſcriptural Expreſſions.</hi> For this the Reader may be refer'd to the Half-ſheet that is intitled, <hi>The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliſts Chriſtian Condeſcenſion conſider'd.</hi> The Reaſons of this Condeſcenſion are, that it ſeems the Orthodox Expreſſions may in ſome meaſure be taken in a Latitudinarian Senſe, and that whatſoever admits of a tolerable Conſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, tho otherwiſe uncouth and unſcriptural, may be ſubmitted to for Peace ſake, till Men at leaſt may have had the time and means to be better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, and whilſt the Goſpel Terms of Communion are not yet ſufficiently known. Thoſe who are perſuaded of the Validity of theſe Reaſons, may uſe this Condeſcenſion, tho on the other hand they believe, that the unſcriptural Expreſſions are extremely improper, and ſubject to great Inconveniences. They may ſtudy to take theſe Expreſſions in a good ſenſe, that they may uſe them with Devotion: But ſeeing it is <hi>Neceſſity</hi> in great part, in this caſe, that juſtifies their Compliance, they ought not to affect the uſe of them more than needs muſt; and ſurely they ought not ſo to plead for the unſcriptural
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:131897:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Terms, as to give them the preference before the Terms of Scripture, or as to condemn them that ſcruple the Uſe of unſcriptural Expreſſions. They ought not to accommodate themſelves to unſcriptural Expreſſions out of worldly Intereſt, or that they may enjoy Eaſe and Pleaſure in this World, (that were certainly to be in a ſtate of Damnation) but that they may labour more uſefully, and may be in a greater Capacity to promote the Truth. They ought therefore to embrace all occaſions to do this, and they ought to do it zealouſly and ſtrenuouſly, if they will ſave their Souls. 'Tis wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful indeed how Men generally are wanting in what they might do for the Truth! But yet, all charitable Condeſcenſion notwithſtanding, they ought not to be aſham'd of or to deny the Truth, but muſt be ready, if occaſion be, to ſacrifice even themſelves for the Truth's ſake. A Man that writes <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions</hi> concerning the Orthodox Doctrines, may profeſs <hi>that the Diſſent and Controverſy (on both ſides) is only from a Miſapprehenſion of one another's Senſe and Meaning,</hi> &amp;c. Thus ſome Perſons may conſcientiouſly condeſcend to the uſe of unſcriptural Terms.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Others, who are no leſs ſincere, may ſcruple the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of theſe Expreſſions.</hi> They may think them paſſable in Articles of Peace, but doubt whether they are reverent enough in public Acts of Religion. They may fear that it is too uncouth to ſay, <hi>O Son of David</hi> have Mercy on us, meaning, <hi>O God who dwelleſt in the Son of David</hi> have Mercy on us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Eſpecially ſeeing how thoſe who ſtretch the Chriſtian Condeſcenſion ſo far, are accus'd of Hypocriſy by ſome Writers, they are loth to appear obnoxious to ſo foul an Aſperſion. Beſides, they may reckon that Men have had ſufficient time to conſider and bethink themſelves; and ſeeing that all this while they have not ſeriouſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd themſelves to the means of Information in a matter of this vaſt moment, or have ſlighted and have not at all regarded all that has been written, they may think that they ought to go out from among them, and look on them as Men that are reſolv'd to ſhut up the Key of Knowledg.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Thoſe, on whom it is incumbent, ſhould eſtabliſh the Scriptural or Goſpel Terms of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi> This is particularly made out in the <hi>Irenicum Magnum,</hi> in a Sheet concerning <hi>Subſcriptions to Articles of Communion,</hi> and another in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled, <hi>The Conſequences of the Modaliſts Syſtem.</hi> This Temperament of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Terms is us'd in our Liturgy, with reſpect to the Queſtions concerning Predeſtination. It would not be more difficult to content our ſelves with the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Terms of Scripture in all other reſpects. If we do it not, we leave Stones of ſtumbling in the way, we needleſly cauſe Diviſions and are guilty of Schiſm, and contradict the fundamental Principles of Proteſtants. We reproach the Scripture, as if it were not a perfect or ſufficient Rule. We leave not to others the Liberty of diſcerning. We act as if we were infallible. We ſet up our ſelves as magiſterial Judges of Controverſies. We exerciſe Dominion over other mens Faith. We oppreſs mens Conſciences, and endanger their Salvation. In fine, we take away the Key of Knowledg, and run the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar of cruſhing the Truth, and of being found violently to fight againſt God.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
